RG 028:004, Commission on State Government Organization, 1949-1950
Connecticut State Library
Commission on State Government Organization records
circa 1940-1950
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. Commission on State Government Organization
13 cubic feet
The Commission used nineteen survey units to study various aspects of state government and make organizational recommendations.
RG028_004
T002705 (except where noted)
Historical Note
The Commission was established under Special Act No. 28, approved March 31, 1949, for the purpose of studying, “all the functions of the state government” in order to prepare findings and recommendations, including proposed legislation, for the General Assembly and the Governor. The five appointed members were led by Carter W. Atkins, Chairman, and Ralph P. Sollott served as Staff Director. A technical staff numbering more than a hundred in all carried on the research and investigatory work for the Commission, which met frequently to discuss preliminary and interim reports and make the necessary policy decisions. Nineteen “survey units” worked on various aspects of the state government and prepared detailed reports and recommendations. After reviewing these, the Commission submitted its own report on February 27, 1950.
Scope and Contents
Includes meeting material such as agenda and reference material, a general file arranged by unit that includes correspondence, working papers, studies and reports, Material on government organization, Staff Director's files, Questionnaires for legislators, press clippings and recordings of radio interviews.
Related Material
RG 028:001, Commission to Investigate the Advisability of Consolidating Certain State Boards and Commission and to Investigate the Public Health Laws, 1915.
RG 028:002, Commission on Reorganization of State Departments, 1935-1937.
RG 028:003, Commission to Study the Integration of the State Judicial System, 1943-1945.
RG 028:005, Commission on Services and Expenditures (Etherington Commission), 1971.
RG 028:006, Committee on the Structure of State Government (Filer Committee), 1975-1977.
RG 028:007, Human Services Reorganization Commission, 1977-1979.
RG 028:008, Governor's Study Group on Limitation on Expenditures, 1978-1979.
RG 028:009, Commission to Study the Management of State Government (Thomas Commission), 1989-1991.
RG 028:010, Commission to Effect Government Reorganization (Hull-Harper Commission), 1991-1992.
RG 005:031 Gov. Chester Bowles, Box 532, "State Government Organization Commission."
Index Terms
Persons:
Atkins, Carter W; Sollott, Ralph P
Organizations:
Connecticut. Commission on State Government Organization
Subjects:
Administrative agencies -- Connecticut; Connecticut -- Politics and government; Connecticut. Commission on State Government Organization -- Records and correspondence; Executive departments -- Connecticut; State governments -- Connecticut
Document Types:
Agendas (administrative records); Clippings; Correspondence; Questionnaires; Press releases; Reports; Sound recordings
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Acquisition Information
It is not clear how the records were transferred into the Connecticut State Library. The minutes of meetings of the Commission, which appear to have been with the records at some point, have evidently been lost. The final report, The Report, was published in February 1950 and is available in the Library.
Container List
- Records, circa 1940-1950
  - 1. Agenda for meetings and related documents, 1949 May-1950 June (Box 1-2)
    Type agenda, together with documents, reference materials, drafts for discussion and other papers submitted to or prepared for the Commission.
    In three looseleaf binders, each arranged more or less chronologically and with some duplication of items in the three.
  - 2. General File, 1949
    Includes correspondence, working papers, studies, interim, preliminary and special reports, final reports and other materials related to the work of the survey units.
    Arranged by survey unit.
    - 1. Executive (Box 3)
      Covers Governor; Secretary of the State; Attorney General.
    - 2. Fiscal (Box 3-4)
      Covers Department of Finance & Control with Office of the Commissioner, Budget Division, Purchasing Division, Personnel Division; Governor's Contingent Fund; Advisory Personnel Committee; Finance Advisory Committee; Comptroller; Treasurer; Investment Committee; Tax Department; Tax Department; Employees Retirement (Comptroller); Teachers' Retirement Board; Personnel Study Committee.
    - 3. Education (Box 5)
      Covers State Board of Education with Board & Control Administrative Div., Rural Supervisory Service, State Aid Grants, Public School Building Commission; Higher Education with University of Connecticut & Storrs Agricultural Experiment Station, State Teachers' Colleges (State Board); Special Education with Vocational Education, Vocational Rehabilitation (State Board), Mystic Oral School, American School for the Deaf, Board of Education for the Blind; Libraries, Museums & Memorials with State Library, United Spanish War Veterans, Henry Whitfield House Trustees, Israel Putnam Campground Commission, Ford Griswold Groton Monument Association, Connecticut Historical Society, Office of the State Editor; Education Study Committee.
    - 4. Health (Box 6)
      Covers Department of Health; Mosquito Control Board; Interstate Sanitation Commission; Commissioner of Food & Drugs.
    - 5. Highways, docks and bridges (Box 7)
      Covers Highway department; Highway Safety Commission; Merritt Parkway Commission; Groton-New London Bridge Commission; East Hartford-Hartford Bridge Commission; Old Lyme-Old Saybrook Bridge Commission; Commissioners of Steamship Terminals.
    - 6. Public works (Box 7-8)
      Covers Department of Public Works (Comptroller-Real Assets); Humane & Welfare Institutions Building Program Commission; State Housing Department.
    - 7. Industrial relations (Box 8)
      Covers Commissioner of Labor & Factory Inspection; Workmen's Compensation Commission; Unemployment Commissioners; Labor Wage Board - State Buildings, Labor Wage Board - Roads & Bridges, Inter-Racial Commission.
    - 8. Agriculture (Box 9)
      Covers Agriculture with Commissioner of Farms & Markets, Agricultural Experiment Station, Regional Marketing Authority; Conservation with Board of Fisheries and Game, Park and Forest Commission, Commission on Forests and Wild Life, Board of Shell Fisheries, Atlantic States Marine Fisheries Commission, Water Commission, Geological & Natural History Survey Commission; Development with Connecticut Development Commission.
    - 9. Regulative agencies (Box 9-10)
      Covers Department of Motor Vehicles; Department of Aeronautics; Insurance Department; Banking Department; Public Utilities Commission; Liquor Control Commission; Milk Administrator.
    - 10. Licensing and examining boards (Box 10)
      Covers Board of Accountancy; Architectural Examining Board; Athletic Commission; Board of Examiners of Barbers; Board of Examiners in Chiropody; Dental Commissioners; Board of Examiners of Embalmers; Board of Healing Arts; Homeopathic Medical Examining Board; Medical Examining Board; Board of Examiners in Midwifery; Board of Natureopathic Examiners; Board of Examiners for Nursing; Commission of Opticians; Board of Examiners in Optometry; Osteopathic Examining Board; Commissioners of Pharmacy; Board of Examiners for Physiotherapy Technicians; Board of Registration Professional Engineers and Land Surveyors; Board of Examiners of Psychologists; Tree Protection Examining Board; Board of Registration and Examination Veterinary.
    - 11a. Police and Fire (Box 10)
      Covers Department of State Police; State Police Association; State Firemen's Association.
    - 11b. Military (Box 11)
      Covers Military Department (Including National Guard, Naval Militia).
    - 12. Welfare (Box 11-12)
      Covers Office of the Commissioner; Division of Public Assistance; Division of Child Welfare; Public Welfare Council; Soldiers, Sailors and Marines' Fund Board of Trustees.
    - 13. Hospitals (Box 12-13)
      Covers Tuberculosis Commission with Administration, Surgical Unit, Seaside Sanatorium, Uncas-on-Thames Sanatorium, Undercliff Sanatorium, Cedarcrest Sanatorium, Laurel Heights Sanatorium; Veterans' Home & Hospital Commission; Commission on Alcoholism; Commission on Care of Chronically Ill, Aged & Infirm; Mental Health with Fairfield State Hospital, Connecticut State Hospital, Norwich State Hospital, Southbury Training School, Mansfield Training School & Hospital, Mansfield-Southbury Social Service Division; General Hospitals; Capital Improvements with agencies not specified in recommendations of the Humane & Welfare Building Program Commission.
    - 14. Corrections (Box 13-14)
      Covers Connecticut State Prison; Connecticut Reformatory; State Farm for Women; Long Lane School; Connecticut School for Boys; Connecticut Prison Association; Board of Pardons.
    - 15a. Purchasing and procurement (Box 14)
    - 15b. Land, records management, communications (Box 14-15)
    - 16. Research and statistics (Box 15-16)
    - 17. Legislative (Box 16)
      Covers General Assembly; Legislative Grants; Legislative Council; Legislative Research Department; Commission to Revise General Statutes; Commission on Uniform Legislation; Commission on Intergovernmental Cooperation; Auditors of Public Accounts.
    - 18. Judicial (Box 16-17)
      Covers Courts with Supreme Court of Errors, Superior Court, Court of Common Pleas, Juvenile Court, Traffic Court of Danbury; Assemblies and Rewards with Municipal Court Assembly, Trial Justice Assembly, Judicial Council, Rewards for the Apprehension of Criminals.
    - 19. Constitution (Box 17-18)
  - 3. Material on government organization elsewhere, circa 1940-1950 (Box 19-20)
    Correspondence, documents, bills, laws and other reference materials pertaining to government organization studies in other states and in the Federal Government (Hoover Commission).
    Arranged by subject in four looseleaf binders.
  - 4. Staff Directors' Files, 1949-1950 (Box 21)
    These appear to be selected files from among the administrative and office files of the Commission and of Mr. Sollott.
    - Summary of allotments and expenditures of the Commission (Box 21)
    - Drafts and reprint of article "All the Functions of State Government", 1950 April (Box 21)
    - File on the Citizens Committee organized to explain and support the work of the Commission (Box 21)
    - Draft materials for the Commission's final report (Box 21)
    - Examples and Comment file (Box 21)
    - Copies of articles on management principles and techniques (Box 21)
    - Draft organization charts (Box 21)
    - List of survey units and principal staff (Box 21)
  - 5. Questionnaires for legislators, 1949 October-December (Box 22)
    Questionnaires asking the opinions of members of the General Assembly on various aspects of the state budget, revenue and government organization, program and review process, together with analyses of their replies. There is also an undated list of House members and their committee assignments.
  - 6. Press clippings, 1949-1950 (Box 23-24)
    Clippings, mostly mounted, of items from Connecticut newspapers pertaining to the work of the Commission. The mounted material is in chronological order.
  - 7. Radio interviews, 1950; T003299; 3 sound discs (1 container) (Volume Item 1)